Empresses in the Palace—the Legend of Zhen Huan
Adopted from the novel by Liu Lian Zi
[translators] Carsen and Maxwell
[join team or mailing list] carsenwei@yahoo.com
[communication homepage] liberapay.com/ZHZSubbers
Theme: Unfortunate Love
Perturbed by the thoughts on my mind
no matter how hard I try to sever my love.
I could give away my crown for the beauty by my side,
but the wheel of fortune turns weals into woes,
and woes into weals.
No one is the master of their own destiny,
the vicissitudes throughout their life.
For all the lovers in the world,
who can break the spell of romance?
I could give away my crown for the beauty by my side,
but the wheel of fortune turns weals into woes,
and woes into weals.
No one is the master of their own destiny,
the vicissitudes throughout their life.
For all the lovers in the world,
who can break the spell of romance?
Who can break the spell of romance?
[join team or mailing list] carsenwei@yahoo.com
[communication homepage] liberapay.com/ZHZSubbers
Your Majesty stayed up late with Lady Shen last night.
Why didn't Your Majesty sleep in for a bit?
All the joy aside,
I have to hold court in the morning.
You didn't sleep well either, did you?
For one thing, I was overjoyed;
for another, I must ensure the the Imperial Infirmary
is able to take care of Lady Shen.
Your hard work is appreciated.
Noble Lady Shen ...
What about her, Your Majesty?
I wish to promote Noble Lady Shen.
Your Majesty is very fond of Lady Shen,
and now she is with child.
Her promotion is reasonably expected.
However, there is no precedent for a concubine
to be promoted upon conception or delivery.
It's not entirely because of her pregnancy.
Her stable personality is a rarity.
That is true.
Compared to Lady Sourire's keen intellect,
Lady Shen is responsible and decorous.
Does Your Majesty intend to promote
Lady Shen to Concubine?
- She's worthy of the title.
- Absolutely.
In this way, however, there will be two concubines
as the heads of the Palace of Universal Happiness.
I'm afraid it will be inconvenient for Lady Shen
to move to another palace in her pregnancy.
Why don't we double her happiness
when her child is born?
You're right.
But I feel obliged to reward her.
Jewelry is all too trivial.
Since her promotion is temporarily delayed,
I wish to give her an honorary name in advance.
Your Majesty must have a name in mind already.
I'm thinking of naming her Vertu [惠Hui].
Hmm, that perfectly describes her.
Lady Sourire and Lady Shen are like sisters.
Now they're finally equal.
What a joyous occasion that your wish came true!
I don't see the joy of that.
All of a sudden I'm restricted to do this and that.
It's such a bore!
There's still nine months to come.
But the time will fly by.
Jinxi said that you will reunite with your family
in the 8th month of your pregnancy.
Your mother will enter the palace to take care of you.
For real? That'll be great!
I’ve set my sights on the baby in your belly.
When will I be his honorary mother?
[similar to the role of a godmother but non-religious]
What use are you as an honorary mother?
You'll be a mother soon as well.
We don't even know yet whether it's a boy or a girl.
I'll take anything!
I wish it is a prince, upon whom
I can rely on for the rest of my life.
For the place you hold in His Majesty's heart,
he will love a girl just as much as a boy.
I'm afraid you'll be promoted again while you're still sitting the month [postpartum confinement].
Don't make fun of me.
I was going to tell you something important,
which I remembered when I woke up this morning.
What could possibly be
more important than your pregnancy?
This is a serious matter.
Consort Fleur might get back on her feet.
I'm afraid that you won't
be able to deal with her on your own.
Honestly, I do not expect His Majesty
to devote himself to just one woman.
Someone might take advantage of
the vacuum during my pregnancy.
Are you suggesting ... that we bring Lingrong here?
Exactly.
Look at you!
You were the one who called her ruthless.
Now you wish she was here.
Well, being ruthless has its own benefits.
We need to plan ahead for you.
We won't be out of our wits
in event of a crisis if she's with us.
I will make a request to His Majesty
at his earliest convenience.
I don't believe he would refuse.
He'll give anything to his number-one concubine.
But you must not worry yourself over anything.
Your health is our top priority.
You're right.
Sourire!
You've finally arrived.
- How was the trip?
- It was all right.
You shouldn't have waited for me outside.
It's such a hot day.
I hope you are not drenched in sweat.
I was permitted to come here at Meizhuang's bidding.
How is she?
Everything's fine with her.
She's even happier now that you're here.
The eunuchs were saying that
His Majesty indulges all of Meizhuang's desires.
"Seeing is believing."
You'll see for yourself.
But before that, we shall pay respect to His Majesty.
Yes, certainly.
Prince, you've been waiting here for half a day.
You might get sun stroke if you stay here.
Mr Su.
Peace to Lady Sourire.
Peace to Companion An.
Mr Su, who is the kid?
That is the Fourth Prince.
He wishes to see His Majesty.
The Fourth Prince?
I've never heard of him.
He's been living in the Summer Palace.
Does His Majesty not have time to see the Fourth Prince?
I'm afraid His Majesty is not in the mood to see anyone.
My Ladies, you may come at another time.
Sourire, shall we ...
shall we go back for now?
What a poor kid!
Sir, may I trouble you to send the Fourth Prince
lotus seed soup to relieve summer heat?
I will, My Lady.
Now that you're here, the quiet garden will be livelier.
I would not be able to come were it not for you two.
Has Consort Fleur mended her fences with His Majesty?
She lives away from His Majesty's residence.
They don't get to see each other a lot.
Peace to My Ladies.
I bow in respect before Lady Sourire.
Peace and grace to Your Highness.
[The prince addresses her this way to show respect.]
Madam Zhang, this is Lady Sourire.
My Lady.
Please rise, Fourth Prince.
We've never met before.
How did you know who I am?
I saw Your Highness outside the Governance Hall.
I felt that you are an amiable person even by a distant glimpse.
That is how I met Your Highness.
And Your Highness met me as well.
Likewise, I share the same sentiment.
It was a great pleasure to meet Your Highness.
Thank you.
This is Companion An.
Peace to Your Highness.
My Pleasure.
Lingrong, how about you go check on your residence?
I will go with you to visit Meizhuang later.
I shall take my leave.
- Vermilion, please go with her.
- Yes.
Madam Zhang, I wish to have a word with Lady Sourire.
Can you stand aside?
Madam Zhang seems to care a lot for you.
What would you like to say to me
that she can't even listen to?
I hope Your Highness will forgive my intruding,
but I thought you could answer my question
for you know Father the best as his favorite concubine.
Your Highness, I simply wish to know ...
Is it true that father dislikes me.
Why would you think that way?
Your Father is just too busy.
But why has he been keeping me here
for all these years and never visits me?
And he never allows me to pay respect to him
to fulfill my filial piety?
His Majesty is busy administering
all things under heaven.
While you've been living here and rarely seen His Majesty,
he cares about you no less than the Fifth Prince.
The Fifth Prince has been living outside the palace as well.
But the Fifth Prince has a mother.
My mother was disdained for her humble background.
A person's value comes from within himself.
Although I know nothing about your mother,
I'm sure she loves you
as much as every mother loves their child.
It doesn't matter what people think about you.
It's what you think of yourself that counts!
In days to come, they will not dare to
have the least contempt for you.
For real?
You wouldn't have come to ask me if you didn't trust me.
I appreciate Your Highness's advice!
But I wonder why you would trust me the first time we meet.
I believe that a concubine does not win
Father's affection with nothing.
And Your Highness is not even afraid of Consort Fleur.
I admire you as a person possessing bravery and brains.
I do not deserve your flattery.
I wish you will remember that
instead of admiring a person, become them.
Is Father really very busy?
If so, I will administer the country for him when I grow up.
Aiya,
you must not say such things.
- Would you like some snacks?
- For sure!
Jiuzhou Qingyan
(The Peaceful Nine States)
I really like this place!
It's so nice and cool in here.
And the music from the lake
can be best appreciated in here.
The palace rules only allow the highly ranked noblemen
to visit the concubines on important occasions.
I do not recognize any of the lords and ladies.
Do you know who they are?
That is Lord V, State Prince Heng,
with his Prince Consort [secondary wife].
State Prince Heng [prince of the first rank]
The first one from left looks very dignified.
He inspires awe in me.
But he seems very nice to his wife.
(State Prince Dun)
That is Lord X, whose mother was the younger sister
of the empress of the prior emperor.
That is why he has an air of authority.
However, the prior emperor wasn't very fond of
Lord X for his notorious short temper.
But Lord X is extremely nice to his wife.
They say a real man is defined by his power,
but in my eyes, a real man is defined by his love for his family.
Yun-e, I'd like to make a toast
to you and your wife.
I thank Your Majesty.
Sourire, State Prince Dun seems
disrespectful to His Majesty.
Why is His Majesty so respectful to him?
After the battle for the throne among the nine princes,
His Majesty has to stabilize the government.
I wonder what's keeping Yunli this time.
He still hasn't appeared.
Your Majesty knows how he is.
( Venerable Prince Shen [prince of the third rank] )
He follows no rule.
A family banquet isn't a big deal after all.
I'll let him be.
Lady Vertu, that is a very nice hairpin you're wearing.
Is it the new gift from the Empress Dowager?
Yes.
The Empress Dowager specially had the hairpin sent here to congratulate Lady Vertu on her pregnancy.
The Two Gods of Harmony on the hairpin will
bless her with plentiful children and good fortune.
This is a special gift because the Empress Dowager
received it when she was pregnant with Lord XIV.
On that account, we can see how much the Empress Dowager is looking forward to Lady Vertu's child.
I can't wait to see what a cute prince it will be.
It's not necessarily a prince.
I'm hoping that it is a princess as adorable as Wenyi.
Enjoy.
(Consort Honnête)
Her Highness Consort Honnête.
May peace and grace be with Your Majesties.
Rise.
I thank Your Majesty.
Your Majesty has obtained
reminiscence (in a new concubine).
You've kept the same eye for all these years.
You shouldn't have come on such a scorching day.
We're just having a meal.
It's nothing significant.
This is a joyous occasion for Wenyi.
I must come to celebrate for her.
I haven't seen her for a long time.
- Take your seat.
- I thank Your Majesty.
Wenyi was just one month old when I last saw her.
Bring Wenyi to greet Her Highness quickly.
I would really like to hold her in my arms.
But I don't have the strength to.
Auspice.
The choker was part of your dowries.
Why would you give such a valuable gift to a small child?
Your Majesty has a good memory.
Considering my persisting health condition,
it will come of no use if I keep it.
It is a perfect gift for the adorable princess.
I thank Your Highness on behalf of Wenyi.
My pleasure.
[join team or mailing list] carsenwei@yahoo.com
[communication homepage] liberapay.com/ZHZSubbers
I wish to go for a walk.
If His Majesty inquire, tell him I'll be back shortly.
Let's stop here for a bit.
I'm tired from walking.
Me as well.
Look, there are koi fish.
Hold this for me.
- My Lady, why are you taking off your shoes?
- It's all right.
But what if people see you?
My Lady, you haven't changed at all.
You are just as playful as when you were at home.
Look, Vermilion, there are so many koi fish!
Great!
Let's go into the water.
The water's rather cold.
Let's go down.
- I'm not going.
- There's nobody around.
This is a new dress.
I can't make it dirty.
You can't make it dirty?
But I can!
My Lady, you have to make me two more dresses!
You'll wait for me up here.
Hold on to me.
Be careful.
My Lady!
Who are you?
Get away!
You would still care about me while you were just
one step away from being a "drenched chicken"?
Who are you?
How dare you be so rude?
Emperor Li Yu described the hands of a lady as
"jade outstretched from emerald blue".
Today I learned that it is true.
But I think that is a more accurate description
for a lady's soft and fair feet.
Get me my shoes.
Here.
Your Lordship must mind your manners.
My Lady ...
Vermilion, this is Noble Prince Guo.
[prince of the second rank]
We've never met before.
Why do you think I am Noble Prince Guo?
Whoever else in the palace would
always carry a flute with himself?
Whoever else could drink the tributary Uygur Rose?
And whoever else dares to be so impertinent?
Do I really reek of alcohol?
My apologies.
Are you a new concubine of my brother?
This is Noble Lady Sourire.
I hope Your Lordship will forgive my offence.
His Lordship is inebriated.
Please take care of him.
Yes.
We should go.
His Majesty is waiting for us.
I bid Your Lordship goodbye.
What is your name?
I am too humble to say my name.
Your Lordship should have some rest and attain sobriety.
You must not tell this to anyone.
Otherwise, I'll have no burial ground for my dead body.
Peace and grace to Your Highness.
Please rise, please rise.
I noticed that you were feeling a bit tipsy.
But when I turned around, you weren't there any more.
The wine was stronger than I expected
so I took a walk to sober up.
We have one celebration after another.
The performance began to pall.
I wish to cut myself some slack.
I wonder if you would like to
join me in the side chamber.
I'm honored to obey Your Highness's gracious invitation.
Your Majesty, may I suggest that we dispense with
formality after the magnificent performance?
A family should not be sitting so stiffly for a meal.
How about we relax a bit on this joyous occasion?
What is your idea?
Each and every concubine present has her talents.
We can write their talents on drawing lots
and the selected person will display her artistic flair.
What does Your Majesty think?
That is a fresh idea.
Let's draw lots.
Yes, Your Majesty.
Sourire, you have a good heart.
But in the palace, it is a bad thing
if all you have is a good heart.
You must remember that
your priority is always to protect yourself.
I'm grateful for Your Highness's advice.
I hope Your Highness can enlighten my dull-witted mind.
You've met the Fourth Prince.
He's bright and healthy.
But why does His Majesty not see him?
Have you thought from the perspective of His Majesty?
Regretfully, I have not.
We've always believed that a mother
becomes distinguished for an esteemed son
but it is also true the other way around.
His Majesty does not like the Forth Prince for his mother was a menial maid at the Rehe Imperial Resort.
It happened when His Majesty was a noble prince.
One day His Majesty had a dispute with Lord VIII
and ended up drinking too much.
That was how he had sexual contact with the maid
and the maid was pregnant with the Fourth Prince.
Lord VIII reported this to the prior emperor
who censured our emperor for his behavior
and nearly deprived him of his title.
The maid was unbearably ugly
and from a humble background.
So His Majesty never liked her
and left her at the resort during her pregnancy.
Adding to her misfortune,
the maid died right after giving birth to her son.
That is why the Fourth Prince
has always been kept in the Summer Palace?
Out of sight, out of mind.
I am grateful for Your Highness's advice.
It's time that we should return.
Your Majesty, the lots are ready for drawing.
Since Lady Vertu is pregnant,
I would like to draw the lots on her behalf.
You are the one who proposed the idea.
Why don't you participate?
I'm afraid I'm not talented in anything
other than making bead tassels.
I think all I can do is
make a bead tassel for every performer.
What does Your Majesty think?
That's lazy, but I'll let it pass.
Aiya, that is interesting.
We've all heard that everyone in
Your Majesty's harem is specially talented.
Today (chuckle), I'll finally open my eyes.
May we have the honor to have
Your Majesty as the first drawer?
You are the mother of the birthday girl.
I hope you can draw for me.
I thank Your Majesty.
Will Your Majesty do us the honor to bestow upon Wenyi
a piece of calligraphy of the 夀[longevity] character?
It is so much pressure on me
to write before so many guests.
Your Majesty writes the finest calligraphy.
Your Majesty must not disappoint
Lady Cao for her lucky draw.
All right, on Wenyi's first birthday,
I will write a gift for her.
I thank Your Majesty on Wenyi's behalf.
Your calligraphy has been advancing.
It's nothing worth mentioning.
I beg Your Majesties will excuse my offence.
I am feeling fatigued.
I'm afraid I cannot enjoy
the rest of the day here with you all.
You should go have a rest if you feel ill.
I'll visit you when I get a chance.
I thank Your Majesty.
While Your Highness's health takes priority,
leaving the banquet so early might dismay His Majesty.
If I stayed, I would instead disappoint the performers.
(sigh) I've seen enough drama on
their pretentious stage.
Out of sight, out of mind.
This one is for Lady Sourire.
Please perform Dance of the Startled Swan.
Your Majesty, Lady Sourire is already as graceful as a swan.
The dance belongs to her.
The dance was created by Consort Mei
of the Tang Dynasty
It had been extinct until Empress Première made
the effort to restore and improve the choreography.
She caused a profound sensation
in the palace and nationwide.
The dance is very difficult to learn.
While a good performer can dance like a swan,
a poor performer will move like a duck.
Lady Sourire is very young.
How can she be experienced in the dance?
Lady Cao, it is too demanding a task that you've assigned.
Nay, Lady Sourire is exceptionally talented.
Any girl can dance the Dance of the Startled Swan.
It is entirely understandable even if
she does not dance as well as Empress Première.
As a family, no one will be strict with her performance.
I'm afraid I would only incur ridicule
for my unpresentable dancing skills.
You don't have to dance if you feel constrained to.
I doubt that anyone could ever compare with
the glamour of Empress Première.
She doesn't need your goad, Consort Fleur.
Lady Sourire will fail to give face to
Lady Cao and Lady Vertu if she refuses to dance.
That will also displease everyone else.
If she dances but not well enough,
it will be such a disgrace to herself.
And even if she dances well,
replicating the dance of Empress Première
will be considered impudent to the late empress.
Your Majesty, I've long heard of this
Lady Sourire of yours.
They say that she is beautiful and talented
except that she cannot dance at all.
I'm afraid she can't even compare
to the geishas of mine.
How can she serve Your Majesty if that's the case?
Aiya,
"The lack of talent is the virtue in a woman."
Why does she have to perform
the Dance of the Startled Swan?
All she needs is a pretty face.
If so, she doesn't deserved to be praised for her talents.
But it will show that His Majesty is shallow for
his favorite concubine being merely a pretty face.
It is difficult to achieve proficiency in the dance.
How about we change to something else?
Your Majesty, Sourire prefers poetry over dance.
May I suggest that she compose
a poem for the princess?
It's been a long time since
the dance was last performed.
I wish to see it as well.
Lady Sourire,
you can perform it the way you like.
Please allow me to get changed, Your Majesty.
I'll be back shortly.
That is certainly allowed,
but I hope she's not giving us the slip.
Stop your crapulent talk before His Majesty.
It is not that you don't know the dance, My Lady.
But now, there's no escape
as if you were on the back of a tiger.
What they want is not a startled swan
but simply a fleeing bird.
Help me get changed.
Your Majesty, I've changed to the costume.
Your Majesty, in addition to the ordinary instruments,
may I offer to play the zither
with Lingrong singing for Lady Sourire?
With great pleasure.
Bring here Endless Longing, the Zither.
The zither was a gift to Consort Serein
from the prior emperor as a symbol of love
along with Eternal Promise, the Flute.
Consort Dowager Serein requested to live in a nunnery
after the prior emperor passed away.
So her zither and flute remain in the palace.
You are fortunate to dance to her zither.
Swift as a startled swan
Graceful as a spiraling dragon
Glorious as the autumn chrysanthemums
Vibrant as the spring pines
Like the moon thinly veiled by the wispy clouds
Like the snow softly whiffles under a gentle breeze
From afar, she looks like the sun
glowing above the rosy sky
Her moves are just the replication of Empress Première.
In nigh, she is a lotus burning above the emerald water
It's graceful, but unoriginal.
It's more important to be respectful than original.
How many more surprises have you kept from me?
My inferior dancing is unworthy
of Your Majesty's flattery.
What marvellous dancing!
It can compare to the best of my geishas.
Yun-e, you made an inappropriate comparison.
Lady Sourire performed the dance
in honor of Consort Mei.
Emperor Xuanzong of Tang referred to
the dance as the Spirit of Mei.
Today, I am fortunate to appreciate
the dance that was originated by Consort Mei.
Don't talk like you witnessed
Consort Mei performing the dance.
Yun-e, while I have not practiced
archery or martial arts as hard as you have,
I did idle my years away reading more books of history.
We Manchus conquered the country with archery.
What is the use of the stinking books?
You're so full of the Han people's books
because your mother is a Han.
Our country needs masters of both pen and sword.
Brothers are like the fingers on one hand.
Everyone has his own strength and weakness.
Don't compare a short finger to a longer one.
Like I said, Your Majesty,
Lady Sourire is extraordinarily talented.
I believe her dance can rival that of Empress Première.
If I recall correctly, not even Consort Fleur was
in the family when Empress Première performed the dance.
Not to mention you, Lady Cao.
How could you possibly know how her dance was?
And how could you possibly
compare it to Lady Sourire's dance?
I hope your Majesty will forgive my offence.
I simply have heard of the dance of Empress Première.
It is my eternal regret to not
have seen the dance of the late empress.
Do you feel tired after all the dancing?
I'm all right, Your Majesty.
It is my loss to not have admired
the glamour of the late empress.
My performance was choreographed
in the light of the music Consort Mei danced to.
My dance to that of Empress Première
is what candlelight is to the moon.
Yunli, you must punish yourself
with three cups of wine for your late arrival.
I just played the flute to accompany
the dancing of your new concubine.
You must let me off on her account.
Eternal Promise, the Flute comes into
divine harmony with Endless Longing, the Zither.
This is Noble Lady Sourire from the Zhen family.
This is Noble Lady Vertu from the Shen family.
And the singer is ...
I'm the Companion from the An family.
You'll be rewarded.
You, come sit with me.
I thank Your Majesty.
You've finally showed up.
Sit next to me!
Consort Fleur, what is the matter with you?
Why would you spoil the mood on such a joyous day?
[translators] Carsen and Maxwell
[join team or mailing list] carsenwei@yahoo.com
[communication homepage] liberapay.com/ZHZSubbers
Theme: The Lonely Phoenix
[phoenix is the symbol of an empress]
I dimly recall the colorful blooms in every summer.
They are as distant as the autumn moon in the water.
He loved me with a volatile heart.
And before I knew it, we fell apart.
Behind me are the promises and longing.
Before me lie the flute and the zither.
I loved you with my body and soul
But you hurt me from head to toe.
My wish ran athwart
and I ended up a fool of my destiny.
My love was the wind-swept flowers from a tree.
A plum bloomed in winter hoping for a fruitful summer.
But the irresistible winds of destiny destroyed her wish.
You can hear the flapping of a phoenix
but you will never see it.
What you see is the falling leaves from the phoenix tree.
The falling leaves from the phoenix tree.